Finding Aid for the Founder’s Capers Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Founder’s Capers Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0151
.02 linear_feet
Biographical Note
The Vanderbilt Faculty Club was a gathering place for faculty and their spouses to socialize and relax. Occasionally groups would gather to perform, one such outlet was this original musical “Founder’s Capers.” This collection specifically contains the sheet music and scripts from their 1961 performance of “Founder’s Capers”. The complete cast was comprised of Vanderbilt professors, family members, and students.
The Vanderbilt faculty that participated in the performances are:
John M. Aden- Associate Professor of English
Samuel F. Babbitt- Lecturer in English
Natalie Babbitt- Music and Lyrics (Samuel Babbitt’s wife)
Robert A. Baldwin- Assistant Professor of Drama
John Compton- Associate Professor of Philosophy
Dwight L. Freshley- Associate Professor of Speech
Langdon Gilkey- Professor of Theology and Director of Graduate Studies in the Theological Field
James Glasse- Associate Professor of Practical Theology and Director of Field Work
Philip Hallie- Professor of Philosophy
Thomas W. Martin- Associate Professor of Chemistry
Elliott Newman- Joe and Morris Werthan Professor of Experimental Medicine
William Pursell- Orchestration
Lawrence Ratner- Associate Professor of Mathematics
Robbie Shackleford- Assistant Professor of Mathematics
Ronald E. Sleeth- Professor of Preaching
Joseph E. Wright- Professor of Speech and Drama, Chairman of the Department, and Director of the University Theatre
There was also a chorus of Faculty wives, students, and anonymous ghost writers that contributed to these performances.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains three archival boxes which amount to 1.251 linear feet in addition to one flat box which is 0.083 linear feet. Within each box there are:
Sheet Music
Scripts
One vinyl Founder’s Capers Record
Paintings
- Scripts and Program Materials
  - Play Script-John Compton’s Copy of Founder’s Capers Act, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Founder’s Capers CD- Book by Samuel F. Babbitt-Faculty Production, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Founder’s Capers Programs- Musical Comedy 3 Acts (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conductor’s Copy- Full Score- William Pursell (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1961 Performance- Sheet Music (11 Songs)
  - Sheet Music- Violins (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Piano (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Cello (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Viola (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Alto (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Tenor (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Alto (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Baritone (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- String Bass (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Trombone (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Trumpets (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Drums (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - - Overture (Box 2)
    - - Opportunity (Box 2)
    - - Fall in Love (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Violins (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - - The life of (Box 2)
    - - Everybody’s a Crook at Heart (Box 2)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Drums (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - - The life of (Box 2)
    - - Everybody’s a Crook at Heart (Box 2)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- String Bass (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - - The life of (Box 2)
    - - Everybody’s a Crook at Heart (Box 2)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Cello (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - - Everybody’s a Crook at Heart (Box 2)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Flute (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - - Everybody’s a Crook at Heart (Box 2)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Trombone (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - - The life of (Box 2)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Trumpet (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - - The life of (Box 2)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Piano (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - - My Heart’s my Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Viola Orchestra (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - - My Heart’s my Own (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Alto (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - The Life of (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Clarinet/Bass Clarinet (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - - Everyone’s a Crook at Heart (Box 2)
    - - Poor Maude (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Saxophone (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - - My Heart’s My Own (Box 2)
    - - The Life of (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Baritone and Oboe (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - - The Life of (Box 2)
    - - Everyone’s a Crook at Heart (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Violins (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - - When Loves Comes (Box 2)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
    - - Lullaby (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Viola Orchestra (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - - When Loves Comes (Box 2)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
    - - Lullaby (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Piano (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - - When Loves Comes (Box 2)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
    - - Lullaby (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Bass (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - - When Loves Comes (Box 2)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
    - - Lullaby (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Cello (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - - When Loves Comes (Box 2)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Piano and Flute (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - - When Love Comes (Box 2)
    - - Lullaby (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Trumpet and Trombone (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Drums and Alto (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
  - Sheet Music- Baritone and Tenor (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - - A Statue of Me (Box 2)
    - - Men’s Sana (Box 2)
- 1961 Performance- Sheet Music (8 Songs)
  - Sheet Music- Violins (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - - Let Me Stay with You (Box 3)
    - - I’d Rather Stay Home (Box 3)
    - - Alma Mater (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Bass/ Bass Clarinet (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - - Let Me Stay with You (Box 3)
    - - I’d Rather Stay Home (Box 3)
    - - Alma Mater (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Viola (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - - Let me Stay with You (Box 3)
    - - Alma Mater (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Clarinet (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - - Let me stay with You (Box 3)
    - - Alma Mater (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Piano (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - - I’d Rather Stay Home (Box 3)
    - - Alma Mater (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Trumpet and Trombone (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - - I’d Rather Stay Home (Box 3)
    - - Alma Mater (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Drums and Flutes (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - - I’d Rather Stay Home (Box 3)
    - - Alma Mater (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Alto, Tenor, Baritone (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - - I’d Rather Stay Home (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Violins (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Viola (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Trumpet (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Trombone (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Drums (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Bass (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Alto and Tenor Saxophone (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Flute and Cello (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - Fight Song Dirge (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Piano and Clarinet (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - - Anonymous Fight Song (Box 3)
    - - The Story of my Life (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Violins (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - - Nothing will Ever be the Same (Box 3)
    - - The Life of a Wife of an Egghead (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Clarinet and Bass Clarinet (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - - Nothing Will Ever be the Same (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Piano and Cello (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - - Nothing Will Ever be the Same (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- Viola and Flute (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - - Nothing Will Ever be the Same (Box 3)
  - Sheet Music- String Bass, Trumpet, Oboe (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - - Nothing Will Ever be the Same (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Founder’s Capers Vinyl Record- Original Cast Recording, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Set Design #1 (Laboratory Sketch) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Set Design #2 (Lockers Sketch) (Box 4, Folder 3)